Just a second, I'll see if I can set off my own.
see if I can set up my own
Thank you.
I wanted to know how we can change the Zoom meeting so I want to connect to my own Zoom
meeting.
All right.
So, let's get started.
Yeah.
It's somehow safe with the headphones, with the Zoom or I know, right?
This is right here.
So this panel right here is specifically for Zoom.
So you will see anything you need to see for Zoom on here.
So what were you looking at?
I just want to join to the attendees.
Yeah.
Yeah. Just end this meeting and then you want to start a new meeting?
Oh, I see. No, no, I don't. So yeah, I'm good.
Okay. Okay, you're good? Okay.
Thank you.
All right, no problem.
All right.
Okay, so let's start by going over the syllabus.
My name is Salman Barsa and so we're going to learn about algorithms.
So, this is a graduate course, but it's very similar to an undergrad algorithms course.
It's a little bit different, but it's mainly the same course.
So my office is a CDM715.
And this is my phone number you can find here.
My e-mail.
feel free to send me email if you have any questions. So the office hours are on
Tuesdays 4 to 5 30 just before the class so there is this zoom meeting room for
the office hours if you wanted to join and but if you can also come in person
just let me know beforehand if you wanted to come in person for the office
hours. So this is an introductory course to design an analysis of algorithms and
we will learn about some basic concepts in algorithms like a runtime. What's a
runtime? How to compute runtime of algorithms. So we will see some basic but
very important algorithms for search, sort, and some graph algorithms. And also we
studied different methods or what we call paradigms of algorithm design which
are dynamic programming, divide and conquer, greedy method. So this will be
covered in the course. So I don't have a specific board but we are mostly on the
lecture notes but we have a book here which is freely available and I use it
only for homework okay but if you are interested also you can read it and it's
very nice and it has a lot of explanations about the algorithms we
study but our algorithms are very basic and fundamental you can find them
everywhere so if you just search on the internet and there are many resources
for them but this book also has a lot of practice questions which is very good
it's also freely available so about attendance so attendance will have some
positive effect on your grades like so implicit and explicit so implicit is
that you always if you attend the class so it's definitely has some effect on
your grades but I haven't made the attendance mandatory so it doesn't have
a negative effect but it will have some positive effect if you attend the
classes so I suggest you just you attend all the sessions mean not only
this class also other classes it's very important for you. Alright so the grades
are distributed as follows so we will have four or five assignments this will
be 40 percent of the grade and so this is the part that you want to make sure
that you get this grade so this is something you do at home and so the
assignments are also not very difficult so you have a lot of time to do them and
And we have midterm exam and final exam.
Midterm is on the fifth week, so the fifth session,
which would be Tuesday, October 13th.
And so you will, so the in-person class will have the midterm
in the class and the online students will have to register
for a proctored exam.
So all of the exams are proctored.
So the final exam is on again here at the same time and classroom,
but that would be on during the week of exams.
So for us that would be November 24th.
So again, online students, they have to register for a proctored exam.
So the topics we will cover, so we start with some review of the background
material. So starting today, we cover some math background and some general
introduction to algorithms and later we will see growth of functions and
Runtime analysis, so how to compute the runtimes in simple situations.
And then we'll start the main part by going over divide and conquer technique.
So we'll learn we'll do a conquer algorithm.
Then dynamic programming technique.
So we'll see a couple of dynamic programming algorithms.
And so we see some graph algorithms.
So these graph algorithms you have seen before.
Most probably in data structures course.
And we also discuss if we have time, one or two greedy algorithms.
So each time, each session, usually I teach one algorithm.
And so for us, it would be two, right?
So each one and a half hour, I teach one algorithm.
And we also will do some practice.
So the first few sessions we do background material and after that you
have some proper algorithms. Right so after this course you will be able to
use these algorithmic techniques that you've learned in the course and you'll
be able to use them in solving many other problems and the techniques and
And algorithms, we learned as I said, they are very basic and they are used as parts
of bigger algorithms.
So these things you should actually know because if you go anywhere later, you want to design
bigger algorithms, you have to use these as building blocks.
And also, the problems that we study are important problems, so like sort and other problems
that you solve these problems themselves are important examples of problems that
happen in applications and we actually give some solutions for them.
So there's some extra information in syllabus if you're interested. So any questions?
Yeah so for the midterm and the final you said it's open
But the book is online, so would we have to print it out?
Yes, so by open book it means that, for instance, the slides you can print and bring to the class.
Slides and a book.
But as I said, I won't be teaching that book, but I use it only for the homework assignments.
But if you want to bring it, you can bring it.
bring it. Other questions? Sorry, can you repeat that again? You said the midterms are the ones
that are open book? Yes. So if you look at the syllabus, so both midterm and final are open book.
So you can bring book and notes if you want.
Okay. Got it. Other questions?
So if no questions, let's start. So the material which I go over today, you can
find them on D2L. So I always upload the material to D2L before the class.
Ok, so what is an algorithm? So most of you have seen algorithms before. So you
have passed the Data Structures course, which is prerequisite for this course
or before that you might have seen algorithms. In general, we can give quite
a simple definition of an algorithm as a precise description of steps to reach
the solution of a problem. Right? So sometimes the problems they be
they need some mechanical procedure to reach the solution and that the
procedure can be described as a sequence of steps and that's basically an
algorithm so anything that is a sequence of steps towards doing something for
reaching some solution that's an algorithm so you have seen a lot of
of these already, even before coming to the university in high school. For
instance, you have seen how to multiply two numbers together, right? So if you
have two big numbers, so you don't know what the solution is, but you know how to
multiply them. So for instance, I have this number and I have another number
Okay, so you will just write them under each other and then you know there is a way of
computing the product
right and that's an example of an algorithm so it's and you know the
Steps of
Performing this multiplication now it doesn't matter if someone gives you
Let's say five digits or 20 digits. It's the same. So you just apply the same procedure
to this to this number. So it really how many digits we have is not that much
important. Ok, so I will explain more about these terms which are in red. Now
an algorithm needs to be correct. So given the problem... so the algorithm
should actually have a proof that it correctly solves the problem. Okay so this
is a requirement for every algorithm. Now sometimes these proofs are easy and
trivial. So for instance when you do the multiplication you're intuitively you
know that okay so the solution is going to be correct but sometimes it's not
immediate from the algorithm itself that it's actually solving the given problem
and it needs to have a proof of correctness. Now all the algorithms we
discussed in the course they are correct but we usually don't give proofs of
correctness. But it's not hard to actually construct proof of correctness
and they actually make sense intuitively that they should be correct.
Other than one algorithm which is in the Grady method, so there's an algorithm
which actually needs a proof of correctness and I will give that. So
So therefore, in real world so in like the algorithms we study here are simple but in
general always there is an algorithm and there is a mathematical proof that that algorithm
solves the given problem.
All right?
So it's not enough to give just an algorithm.
So one has to actually prove that that algorithm is correct.
You will see also example of this.
another important thing about algorithms is the run time. So the run time is
intuitively how much your algorithm takes to run on an input of certain size.
So the input to the algorithm has a size so it's usually denoted N and the run
time of an algorithm is computed as a function of N. Now we cannot compute
exactly the runtime that the algorithm needs on a certain computer, right?
So if you implement the algorithm and run it on a computer, it might need a
certain time, but we are not able to compute the exact run times of an
algorithm, because it depends on a lot of factors. But we have we can write
basically the run times which count the important operations of these algorithms
so that we can compare them. So for us the important thing about run time is
that we want to compute the run times of functions so that of algorithm so that
we can compare two algorithms together. We should be able to say this one
has a better run time than the other one. Now let's go over more details about
about these terms. So what is the problem? So what type of problem is solved by an
algorithm? So these are problems where the solution needs to be computed. So
sometimes the problems ask about if certain things exist with certain
properties, but if you are not interested in those kind of problems, but
if something needs to be computed then usually there is an algorithm for that
and you are interested only in those kinds of problems. So examples, as I said,
for instance, multiplying two numbers is is a problem that has an algorithm. So
another one, let's say, if you want to know the digits of the number pi. So
there is actually an algorithm that can compute the digits of pi one by one.
Right. So it just wait and you just take it gives you the next digit and then you
weight and it gives you the next digit. So it's possible to compute the digits of
pi one by one. So for instance sorting an array of numbers, so
that's possible, that's an algorithmic problem, so given an array of numbers you
want to sort them. So that's a typical algorithmic problem and now we want to
do it as fast as possible. So actually we'll give algorithms for that
today. So let's say, so this is a sort problem, so sort the following array into
increasing order. And now in this problem we want to do it only using swaps, right?
So what's a swap is when you exchange two elements in your array? So that's a swap.
Now usually in computer science we don't say increasing because you might have
repetition so you might have equal a number so we say non decreasing. But here
because every number is distinct it's it's okay to say increasing. But in
general, for instance, if you have an array like this, so 1, 2, 2, 3, this is not an
increasing sequence because so you this here is equal. So increasing always means
a strictly increasing. So this would say a non-decreasing sequence but here it
doesn't matter because all the numbers are distinct so we say that it's an
increasing order, but in general we should say non-decreasing order. Okay, now
here is a suggested algorithm now some of you might know a better way of sorting
this array using swaps, but let's for now consider this algorithm so we have
two steps. So step one, so scan this array from left to right until you see
two consecutive numbers which are not in order. Say those are ai and ai plus one.
And then so if you don't find such a pair which are not in order, then
everything is in order, right? So if you start from left and go right and every
two consecutive, they are in order so that the left one is smaller than the
right one, then everything is in order. And then the array is sorted. But if you
found a pair which are not in order, then swap them. And then go back to the
first step. Now this is a totally acceptable algorithm, so it's a precise
description of what you need to do. Now we don't know if it eventually sorts the
array or not but it's it's a very well define algorithm
All right, so let's apply the algorithm to this array.
So we start from the left and so if we find it two consecutive one which are
nothing all they were stronger now already here five and two they are not
in order right. So the first one should be smaller so this is five is larger than
two, so I change these two I get two and five. So again I go to step 1 so I start
from here, how I check 2 and 5 so these are in order, 5 and 6, these are in order
but six and one, these are not in order so I swap them. So one comes here, six comes.
Now again if I start from here, again so two and five are in order, five and one
are now not in order so swap them.
Again, I start from here, 2 and 1, not in order, swap them so I get this, 1, 2, again
I start from here, so 1, 2 in order, 2, 5 in order, 5, 6 in order, 3, 6, not in order so
you swap them.
And you can continue like this.
time you start from the left, you go until you find two consecutive numbers
which are not in order, you swap it. So, this is an algorithm. So, it's a precise
description of what to do in English. So, English is totally fine for algorithms.
Actually, almost all of the new algorithms that people develop, they
publish in English. So they just write it in English. So it doesn't need to be
code or something. Okay, so I talked about the types of problems, and what's
the precise description? Now let's see, now as we said the algorithm needs to be
correct. So this algorithm that we have, now is this a correct one or not? So a
correct, what's a correct algorithm? It's an algorithm to solve the given problem
and a mathematical proof that the algorithm solves the given problem. Now
Now is this algorithm correct for sorting the array?
So what is the argument that this actually eventually sorts the array?
Yeah.
It takes off but it always stands to make sure that's in order before it continues going on,
so eventually it will be in order at some point.
Yeah, so.
If eventually this stops, the array will be in order, right?
So but how do you know that eventually it stops?
There would be no pair that's bigger than the other?
Yeah, but how do we know that eventually there will
be no pair that is not in order?
So there has to be some kind of improvement
that we're making each time, right?
So each time we go over step one, we are making some improvement.
So we, and what's that improvement you're making here.
Yeah.
You raise increasing order.
We're doing what?
That raise in increasing order.
That is sorted.
Yeah, you have to say in a more precise way what is raising and increasing order.
but an easy way of saying it is that, so first of all,
it's possible to prove that the algorithm finishes.
So now, when it finishes, then clearly the step one,
everything is in order, right?
So when it finishes.
Now, why it finishes, because, so let
go back here because each time we can say that if we do a swap let's say if I
swap three and six with each other there I never swap these two numbers again
right so each pair of numbers they are swap exactly once I mean at most once
so if you swap six and three you you never swap three and six back again
because you always swap if it's not in order so the next time you see this pair
three and six they will be in order so each pair is wrapped that most once
that's the way to know that it's correct yes so each time you go over a step one
if you if it's not in order you swap something and you kind of consume one
one pair. Yes. And so now how many pairs is there? It's some number, right? So the
number of pairs is like n choose two in general, right? So here you have n equal
like eight. So you have a choose two. This is something like eight times seven
divided by 2. 4 times 7 like 28 many pairs is there and each pair you do once.
So the step 1 you do at most 28 times because each time I use if it's not
already sorted you do a swap so and you each pair you do once so it at most the
the number of pairs, you do a step one.
And after that, everything has to be sorted.
So one way to know this, say, to measure the sorted,
like it's counting each, so after sorting one and two,
or the first two digits, whatever it was,
then it has a bucket where it keeps it and, like, OK,
I have a new n for sorted and then it goes through.
And then you measure if the number of sorted in the sorted list is equal to the number
of items you have in the original list, that's a way to know, okay, we're done sorted.
There might be other ways of showing that this eventually sorts the array, but whatever
you do it, you have to say it in a kind of a precise way.
So the exact weight.
So, for instance, it might be possible to say that, for instance,
the numbers move left or something like that.
So, in those terms, it's also possible.
Now we see another algorithm which is very similar to this one,
and the reasoning for that algorithm is a little bit different
than this. And you see that this is, in general, it wastes a lot of time because we always
come back to the beginning and we go until we find 2 consequently in 1 which are not
in order. So, it's not exactly the best algorithm for sorting. And in general, we'll see also
the runtime in general. So, it's not the best algorithm, but it's good for like a simple
So therefore eventually because you do the swap for each pair of numbers at
most to once so you do this step 1 at most a number of times which is the
total possible pairs and after that it will be sorted. So therefore step one
it's a number of pairs many times is around here. So now in this course as I
said we don't usually give proofs of correctness because the algorithms we see
are actually intuitively they make sense and so as I said so this is the
again the algorithm that is yeah the argument that the algorithm is size
correct so we swap each pair at most once so eventually the algorithm stops
at the step one because the pairs finish basically. So question? So we won't have to prove why it's right then?
What? We won't have to prove why it's right for the most part then? No so and also don't ask about the
groups of correctness. So if there's like in homework, you have a, if we ask to
write an algorithm for something, you don't need to have proof of correctness,
but you have to have the correct algorithm. There's only one algorithm, which
is a Grady algorithm, which is not clear that it's correct. We prove that, so
sometimes the algorithms are, it's not intuitively, it's not clear
why they are correct, so why they are solving the given problem. So in those
cases, one has to actually have the proof of correctness. But otherwise, I mean
intuitively algorithms make sense. Now let's see what is runtime computation.
So now it's basically, as I said, we want to count the time that is taken by the
algorithm but usually we count some important steps so that are so we count
the steps which are important for us so in this algorithm for instance we want
to count the number of swaps right and as we said the number of swaps in this
algorithm is equal to the number of pairs at most. So, now on this particular
instance, we had for instance this much, at most, many pairs, but in general the
algorithm is not for one particular array. It's given for an arbitrary array,
array right. So in general we have a situation like this. We have an arbitrary
array as input and then the input has a size which again it depends on the
problem but here is the size of the array is n, so you have n numbers so
that's also the size of the input. The input is always has a size because the
input is a general. It's not a fixed array so the algorithms are given on
general input and the input has a size. It depends on the problem, so the size
depends on the problem. For sorting problem, so the number of elements that
you have is the size, is usually the size of the input. So again, this is even, this
is not always true, so sometimes size might be something else. Yes?
I'm just scratching this up.
Okay. So the size of the input is usually denoted n. So like here you have n number.
Now if we again repeat what we said for that particular instance, so we have something
like this. So now you do the same algorithm on this general a. How many
swaps does the algorithm perform on an arbitrary with N elements?
So at most it can be like the length of the input array so it can be like 8, 7,
then 654321?
This one at most, the number of pairs.
Okay.
So, but I mean just saying that what is the number
of operations on arbitrary input, it doesn't make sense
because it's not one number.
So it's different for different arrays, right?
So, for instance, for our algorithm,
if the array is already sorted then it takes no swaps
you just go over it and sorted is zero. And that actually happens among all the
inputs. So it happens that sometimes it's sorted. Now it happens that sometimes
you need the most possible number of swaps. Now for an algorithm the runtime
is usually it asks about the worst case situation. So what's the maximum number
of the operations you do on input of size n. So that's the that's the runtime
on input of size n. It's always the maximum. And now here on arrays of size
n we do at most the number of swaps which is the number of pairs and that's
this number. So this number is n choose 2 is n times n minus 1 divided by 2.
That's the number of pairs of, you can create out of n numbers.
So that would be when it's like 8, 7, 6, 5 like?
This is actually, this is this.
Sorry?
Yeah, that's a different thing.
That's not the worst case?
No, the worst case is this.
Oh, okay.
So 8 times 7 divided by 2.
the number of pairs. Right, so therefore this algorithm performs an input of size
n at most this much swaps, that's at most. So now sometimes it does less but it
cannot be more than this. Okay so the runtime on an array of size N is taken
to be the worst case for all arrays of size N. Right? So for inputs of size N the
runtime is the worst case over all the inputs of that size N.
So therefore the running time is a function for instance T of n. So which
assigns to the size of the input which is n the maximum time which is required
by the algorithm on input of size n. Now in this situation we have so for our
algorithm there, t of n is this function. So for instance n square over 2 minus n
over 2 swaps. So if we, because we count the swaps there, but in a different
algorithm we're a different problem we might want to count different things,
So, therefore the runtime is just a function that assigns to the size of the input, the
maximum time that your algorithm takes on that input, so an input of that size.
And now, how you compute time, it depends on the algorithm.
So sometimes you want to count the number of swaps, sometimes you want to count the
number of comparisons and in general we count operations which we think they
are bottlenecks. So in the sense that if we count those we have an idea of the
how after run time of the algorithm up to some constant. So because we cannot
compute exactly all the runtime but up to a constant we are fine. So we'll
discuss this more. Okay, so these are just again, and the comments already made. So
for our algorithm we count the number of swaps at the time as the time required
for the algorithm. So the tn is the maximum number of swaps needed to solve
the error. So and what is TN is this. So questions?
Right so as I said so for any algorithm we recognize some basic operations and we
assume that those basic operations cost to 1 and then we count how many of those
operations are done by the algorithm, for instance we have the swaps there in
that algorithm, we said that how many swaps we do now in some other algorithm
we might actually count the number of comparisons or other things so depending
on the algorithm. So here what I'm saying is that the runtime is not exactly the
runtime, right. So it's the number of the important operations done by the
algorithm. So, and why do we do that? Because all the operations, so if you
count everything that the algorithm does, it's then it becomes a tedious
computation. So it's hard to actually compute exactly how many basic steps
your algorithm does, right. So, for instance, how many memory accesses or
additions or all the operations that is done by the algorithm, it's actually
hard to count all of those so we actually always find important
operations which we think they are the bottleneck and how many of those is
needed for for the algorithm so what's the worst case in terms of those
operations and that will give us the what we call the order of the runtime so it
gives us the runtime up to some constant number some multiplicative constant so
So we will talk also about this in the next session, about the order of Runtimes.
So Runtime Analysis is very important because Runtime of an algorithm is the most important
factor for comparing two algorithms to each other.
So in computer science people are always after better and better algorithms for solving the
same problem. And the most important factor in one algorithm being better
than the other one is that it should be faster. So faster is very important
because some of the problems, which are important problems, if you have a very
slow algorithm then you can it's basically like having no algorithm. And
An algorithm that takes like one year to solve a problem on one million inputs is not useful.
But if you have an algorithm which is, for instance, linear in the size of your input,
so if the size of your input is n, it takes like ten times n to solve the problem,
that's very useful.
That's, that's, then you don't need any other algorithm.
Now there are many problems which we don't know that if they have actually any efficient algorithms.
And there are many problems like sorting that we know different algorithms.
Some of them good running time.
Some of them not good running.
But so running time is very important because I mean that's the most important factor for comparing the algorithms.
And there are also other things like space requirements.
Now space requirement is also important because sometimes there are algorithms that need a lot of memory.
So if your algorithm needs a lot of memory, it's still useless because memory is limited.
So there are also other factors but the most important is run time.
Okay let's see. Now a little about a pseudo, what we call a pseudo code. So the
algorithms that we studied they are intended to be implemented in
different programming languages and they have been implemented so maybe like
there are thousands of implementations for each of them.
so in the different languages we can find implementations and in
implementation of an algorithm in these languages it's it's a precise description
it's actually a very precise description of of that algorithm so it's of the
steps that you need to solve the problem but the code itself is too much precise
So it's actually, the code is too detailed and it has special cases to deal with special situations
and maybe you have some parts for input-output and different things that you have to manage in your code.
So it's not suitable. It's not a human readable.
Right? So if you have a Python code of these algorithms we study, it's not that much useful for us.
So we want to have something which is somehow between English and the code,
so it's more precise than the usual language,
but it's also not that much detail as the code itself.
So that's what is called a pseudocode.
So pseudocode is like a code where you actually allow to use more English language in it.
not actually a programming language. It is like a programming language but it's
more human readable. Okay so now I'll give you some examples of the pseudo-code.
Okay now let's look at the sorting problem. So this is the general sorting
problem. So we are given an array A so it has N elements so the N is the size
of the input and we want to rearrange the numbers in A so that we have, so we
have them in the non-decreasing order. So this is the non-decreasing order.
But that's a sorting problem. So the problem is different than the
algorithm. Right? So you have the problem you might have like 10 different
algorithms to solve the same problem. Now we have this sorting problem and we
give many algorithms to solve this. So we already solve one, so I gave one
algorithm for this. Now here is another one so this is like in a more structured
way in the pseudocode and this is called bubble sort. So we have two loops so it
says that go over the array basically so for I equals one to n. So this outside
loop is just a loop right so it goes from one to n and inside of that
we have another loop which starts from j equals two and goes up to n.
now it again considers aj and aj minus 1.
So now this inner loop,
it looks like that actually starts from the second position.
And it looks at aj and aj minus 1.
So it does similar to what you had in the previous algorithm.
Now, it says that if aj is less than aj minus 1,
so if these two are not in order,
then this is swap. Right. So these three statements here just swapping the AJ and
AJ-1. So it stores AJ in a temporary variable, writes AJ-1 on top of AJ, and
writes temp in AJ-1. So here we could simply, instead of this line, we could
say SUAP AJ and AJ minus 1. Because this is pseudo code. So you could just say
SUAP the two. So in general in a pseudo code, as long as we know an operation
costs a constant amount of time, then you can just write that. So give it a name
and you can write it as long as it's kind of trivial how to expand it. So you could
say here SWF H and HG minus R. Okay now now what is this one's this
algorithms things so let me go back to the original array we had just a second
I go back to this very example
Okay, now it says that you notice that the outside loop it has a variable I, but I
doesn't appear here in the inside loop. So it basically says that repeated this
inner loop n times. Now what is this inner loop so it starts from the second
one and whenever you see this one and previous one is not in order swap them
and then go to the next one if not in order swap them then go to the next one
if not in order swap them and you continue like this until the end. So it
says that at each step compare aj and aj minus 1 this condition means that if
they are not in order. If they are not in order swap them then go to the next j.
So now let's apply this inner loop to this array.
So I write the result here so we start from take on to the J is here now let me
copy that actually it's better
J starts from 2 so this is 2. Now it says look at J and J minus 1. So if a J is less than a J minus 1, swap them.
So that's just simply says that if these two are not in order. Now here so I swap these two. So then I have
2 and 5, and now j goes to the next index.
We go to the next j, and now 6 and 5. So 6 is greater than 5. So this condition is not satisfied.
goes to the next j. Now a j is less than a j minus 1, so it swaps then.
One, six. The next iteration, j goes to the next index. Now again, a j is less than a j minus 1,
swaps them. So three comes here, six goes there.
then J goes to the next index. Now again, 4 is less than 6, so it swaps them.
So, 6, sorry, 4 comes here, 6 goes there. And J goes to the next. 8 is greater than
six so the condition is not satisfied it just goes to the next J7 is less than
eight so it's two absent seven comes here and that's it so that's now we did
one, we did the inner loop once. Now the algorithm, the way it's written says that
now if you do this inner loop, N times the array is sorted. So now we did it once
and that's the result. So now if you repeat this process n times, so again you
come here and you compare these two and if this one is small you swap them and
you go to the next one and so on. Now the claim is that if you do this in a loop
n times, the array is sorted. So now to convince ourselves that this is correct,
so we have to make some kind of improvement when we do this one, this
inner loop once. So now can anyone say what is the improvement we've made when
we went over the inner loop once? So this is now in the previous algorithm
was different but this algorithm when you do the inner loop once there's
actually some concrete thing that we can say happens. That makes us more near
a sorted array. Is it that the biggest number will be the last element? Yes, so
that's correct. So if you, if anywhere you encounter the maximum element of your
array so you go from left to right so if you see the maximum element somewhere so
by the way the code works it will be swapped all the way to the end of the
array because it's larger than anything else so it's always so you will always
have this one and it goes to the next one and then again it's larger it's so
up to the next and so on and it will end up as the last element in your array so
now here you see that 8 is the max of the array. So it's at the end. So after you
do the inner loop once it is guaranteed that the last element is the maximum.
And so, again we don't formally prove this but it's very easy to see right. So
So if you just imagine that the max app here so it's,
the next one is smaller so it will be swapped with the next one.
Then again the next one is smaller, it will be swapped with the next one
as will go up until to the end.
That's why it's called the bubble sort
because the maximum will go up all the way to the end.
It's like a bubble that goes up to the surface.
So now if I do another time this inner loop,
the second maximum will come at the 1 to the last place.
Now if you do it another time, the third maximum will come to the 3 to the last place and so on.
So if you continue doing that, each iteration that you do,
you will play the next maximum in its correct place.
And so after any iterations, it's guaranteed that you will source the error.
Now it might be that this is the worst case that happens. So for instance here
already the the next max two maxima they're already in the correct places.
But that's a this specific instance right? So on other examples so you this
might not happen but after you do the second iteration of this inner loop you
do it a second time then it's guaranteed that the second maximum will be at the
second to last place. To sort the whole array is enough to do repeat these 10
times. So now if we want to compute the runtime of this, so if you want to count
so usually the number of comparisons is counted here. If you count the number of
comparisons then how many comparisons we have here? So, in terms of n, so we have
n numbers. Now, how many times we do this comparison?
I think I'm going to do n minus 1.
n minus 1, that's for one iteration of the outer loop.
For fixed i, we do n minus 1 because it goes from 2 to n.
But we have n different i's.
So n times n minus 1.
So the number of times we do this line is n times n minus 1,
this comparison.
that is independent of the inputs. So if it's sorted or not, you do that much
comparisons. But the swaps are dependent. If you count the swaps, they will be
dependent on the inputs. Right, so, now, this is easier to see that this is a
squared at most and this is roughly in a squared algorithm because it's two
loops so it's n times n minus 1 so we don't need to so the previous one we
had to argue that it stops but this is clearly that it stops but now we have to
argue that at the end is sorted and we are good that it's sorted after this
after n iterations. So, questions? So therefore, the running time of this, if
you write as t of n is, so it depends. So if you want to count the number of
comparisons, so usually we count the number of comparisons, so I know I said
we count a number of swaps in the previous one, but in the sorting
algorithms we usually count the comparison so it's n times n minus 1
comparisons and this is this is quadratic.
and you will see later better algorithms which are not quadratic question if no
question I have some practice problems so as I said we usually do practice
problems in class and these are also uploaded there for online so you can
You can find these .
Do you expect a function?
C of L is the number of components.
No, it's just because there's like an outside table, sometimes it goes on times and for
each time that the outside table turns, we do the inner table.
So, we have some more similar to this computation
to have next session .
So, here we have, this is basically understanding pseudocode.
So it's, there are two algorithms, one of them is for computing just a maximum number
the list and the second one is checking if a given number is prime. Now the
problem asks to just write the runtimes in terms of the input so for
the algorithm 1 the input is just a number of elements in your list if you
want n. For the second algorithm the input size is just a given number. I say
a given number itself.
Thank you.
I can't wait.
I'm going to try it out.
Okay.
Thank you.
so
I can do it with the next step.
Thank you.
you
So, I'm going to use the same way that I'm ready to use.
All right.
Thank you.
Okay, so the way these algorithms are presented as kind of a standard form, so input, output,
and so input, output already tells you the problem, so input is a list of numbers, the
output is the maximum number in the list, so the output tells you what you want to
And this is a trivial thing, right, so you put the first element, so then the zero, for
instance, into the max.
And you know, for each number in your list, you check if that number is greater than max.
If so, then you update your max and that's it and then you return the max.
And I mean if the input number has input list has N elements so the input size is N.
So if we and says we want to count for the maximum algorithm
comes to the worst case number of comparisons.
So the worst case is actually always the same.
So it's always the same number.
So t of n here is just n, right?
Because for each number in the list, you do one comparison.
It's always the same.
it's the best case and worst case all equal. And here, the input is an integer
number and then output is just true or false. So we want to know if the number
is prime or not. So the input size here is the given number itself.
basically what it does is it first checks if the number is at most one. So
it's checking if it's 0 or 1, so if it's 0 or 1, it's not prime, returns false.
Otherwise it tries to find a divisor of the number. So if you remember the number
is prime if it has a divisor, if not prime, if it has a divisor other than
itself and 1. So it starts from 2, and it goes up to the square root of the number
and checks if the reminder of dividing the number by i is 0. If that's the case
then that's a divisor which is not 1 and the number itself so it returns false.
So if you don't return here then at the end it returns true. So that's the
number is prime. Now really for computing the runtime you actually don't need to
know what the code is doing, right? So you can just count based on the bounds of
these loops. So if the original number is n, so the input size is n, then this
This is goes from 2 to the square root of the n.
So t of n is the square root of n minus 1 at most.
So because you want to count the number of times that we take the reminder, which is
this line, so we want to count how many times we execute line 5.
And so now line 5 is in this loop, so it goes from 2 to the square root of n, so the square
root of n minus 1 times.
Now these are really easy for runtime computation, but the purpose is for you to see some examples
of pseudo code.
Now can anyone say, why is it enough to actually go to the square root of the number and not,
let's say the number minus 1.
So if a number is not prime, right,
so you can write it as A times B, right?
and a and b both are greater than 1 and less than n.
So it cannot be that both of them are greater than square root
of n because if both of them are greater than square root
of n, the product will be greater than n.
So there's at least one divisor, which is less than square root of n.
If your number is not prime.
So that's why it's go up the square root of n.
So this is not part of the course, but it's just to know why this is actually correct algorithm.
Yes?
How would you read out line four and algorithm two?
It just go from, it's a for loop that goes from, I goes from two to square root,
There is a square root of your number.
Number is the input, right?
So in Python, for instance, you write what?
So you write range.
Range?
Rewrite something like this.
So, for i in, right?
Yes.
In a range of.
So, here you say, two is qrt of like that n, that number.
But this is, so the Python does it in a different way,
But this is like a classic way on all the other programming languages.
So even this you can write in Python like this.
For instance, in C++, or C, you write for int.
I'm not wrong.
I equals 2 I less than square T of N I plus plus.
And then you write it.
It could be less than or equal to, or just less than?
Is it equal?
Basically.
Yeah, it has to be equal.
Then the present one you have to plus 1.
Here?
Yeah, for the present code.
Yes, you're right, yeah.
So this is, right, it's not inclusive, right?
Yeah, but this is not really code for any language.
This is the same thing you understand.
So it's just a for loop it goes from I equals two to I
equals the square root of number.
All right, so that's it for the first session.
So I just want to check the people who are attending now.
I already marked everyone which is online.
so
Thank you.
Okay, so can you tell your names, starting from here?
Miguel.
Tamahtra.
Aakash Lalarmani.
Yes, me.
Akash Lalarmani.
Valarmani.
So what is your family name?
Lilla Rahmani.
L-I-L-A.
It's not on there.
So sometimes the ordering is a little bit strange.
Yeah, let's type right there.
You, I know you?
Yuhi Wang.
So if we do this once, then the next time I can just check myself.
So it's easier.
This is strange.
All right.
Your full name?
B-A-T.
Oh.
You're also not here, strange, so … you?
Min Min Pen.
Yeah, check.
Okay.
You?
Julian Fargas.
so it's all about a hit
Okay, so...
Blake Jafari?
Yeah, I think I already caught you.
So yeah.
Destiny Wilds.
So you, KSIG.
Some of you I don't find here for some reason.
Thank you.
Thank you, Matthew.
Mike, that's so much more of the very interesting literature.
My child's all right.
Ooh, child's all right.
Thank you.
I think it might not be the latest .
Just writing your original name, what I'm writing.
Yeah.
For some reason this doesn't get updated.
and all the new students, and somehow
not the original people's cycle.
It is just .
So you can see.
Thank you.
All right, just like this.
Let's do it on my desk.
so
So, actually I got this list just now, before I came here, but for some reason
So, thank you.
Okay.
So, let's have a break for about 15 minutes, and then we start again at 35.
Excuse me Professor.
Yes I just wanted to confirm them that I'm actually on the list of Zoom attendees.
I came in a couple minutes later due to some networking issues.
Yeah, I think I already entered. I checked your name here.
Alright, excellent. Yeah, this is Anthony Caranoza. I just wanted to check to make sure.
Okay.
I'm a real agent, for the first time.
I understand.
How do I know I saw it?
It's cool.
Yeah, but I'm real agent, I developed it.
AI algorithm or not.
You were?
I'm being my kids' models and other things.
I just build AI agents.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
So this is kind of my ambition, you know.
we will have an chat box inside the recording page.
And we will get an answer.
So I'm doing a little test.
That's pretty cool.
Thank you.
Have you found anything else so far?
I don't know.
I'll try to try and sort it.
of the slide into the database, semantic database,
in context, and then just give this information
to the user.
That's pretty good.
Yeah.
We will deploy it later to the center.
Oh, that's cool.
We'll do even more things because we can be models.
do you need to get into a new screen?
Thank you.
I think it's definitely a big answer.
I think it's actually a big answer.
I think it's actually a little bit.
I think it's really a big answer.
I think it's really important to me,
it's a big answer, it's really a big answer.
It's really a big answer.
I'm sorry.
You're a teacher.
I'm a school.
I'm a student.
Thank you.
I'm a teacher.
I'm a student.
and then it's doing some fun.
Got some.
Yeah.
That's like a big issue.
Here.
I have an intuition.
No, I have an intuition.
Yeah.
In Portugal.
We have always been a good person on the interview.
I'm sorry you have to leave.
I was so Ugh.
I think I was so close to the meeting.
I don't know the name of Japan.
I'm sorry.
I was there last night that was a good one.
I mean, like this nation soon.
Yeah, and I don't know what this is.
Nice to work out.
This is not a good class here, actually.
Oh, and especially now, all of us.
How about the site of what you think, the boundary?
That's cool.
And you feel like the snowels, or like on the sand,
the buildings.
I think so you're not bad, but you think you want this?
Oh, that's cool.
Yeah.
You're not just a little.
I'm going to go to first.
No.
I'll be to .
I don't remember where it was before about two hours.
.
Yeah.
I'll tell people about the mountains in .
Oh, I didn't know they have .
Yeah.
They have .
Club burgers.
It's like .
i got there and it's like very
I think we're, yeah.
I think it's a little bit.
It smells terrible.
It's like a meme.
It's real.
Yes.
It's such a dramatic city.
It's like a bunch of cards and like .
Yeah, it's three half-tabers, like the rest are huge.
New York guys, they have another fire clock.
They actually have a lot of the different types of but they have a lot of the things.
That's how nice to do.
Oh, you're not, I'm sorry.
It's not like you.
I tried.
Yeah, it was pretty good in the Yankees,
different in the Shakira.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
So you came in from Congo?
Like Groff?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
You two, actually.
Two years.
Oh, shit.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
.
No, Mexican.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
A bunch of some .
How do you watch it?
It was like a pretty good school.
And I was like, oh, nice.
Where did you get away from?
I don't know.
I was from here.
We were from here.
University of California, California, California.
You could do that one.
It was like five since it was coming to me.
It's like two months ago.
And then there was other schools.
It was about other colleges.
Everybody lives in downtown and I'm like,
a very far away.
to teach Russia.
Russia.
Not in jail in Pennsylvania.
Yeah.
It's from the Pennsylvania part of that.
It's nice.
I like to like it.
You want to work up?
Yeah.
Yeah, it is.
I thought we were .
Yeah.
We're going to work for.
I would go out Iran.
Huh?
Iran.
Just like after like ..
I can go into a clean for the air.
.
Yeah.
It's because it seems that we already spike up the...
The next one has an entire Q4.
Two marks, mhm.
And it's like,
And you can do an op,
It's because you can follow the players...
Here we are.
I don't know.
I don't know what's wrong.
what's wrong?
yeah they lost him
yeah they beat piano and they lost
this one is egyptian
so it's not the most easy.
yeah.
yeah, yeah.
yeah, it's kind of good, so I had it.
D'you want to put that on top of the table?
Oh, no.
Yeah.
Yeah, the top.
And I see it.
Yeah.
he lost
Even then, here, if you want to get a new one.
Yeah, probably, yeah.
Probably, probably, probably, just one day.
Here, there's this.
I'm going to be seeing.
And the face is going to be a new one.
Same here, yeah.
Thank you.
Yeah, must be nice, wasn't it?
Did we get through, right?
Thank you.
the , and .
.
I'm trying to get some new increase right now.
So tomorrow and then, yeah.
All right.
We're going to learn some background material.
So first, there's some math.
And after that, some runtime computations.
But first, we have to have some background in math,
and especially the logarithms.
So what's the logarithm?
So, assume that a and b are just numbers greater than 1 and x, y is positive.
So, this is the definition of the logarithm.
So if you have a number a and a to the power z is x,
then by definition log of x equals a is z, right?
So this is equivalent to log of x equals a is z.
So this is the definition, right?
So log of x in base a is the number that if you raise a to that power becomes x.
It gives x.
Okay, so x a, sorry, a to what power becomes, is equal to x?
That's log of x in base a.
So, example.
So, for instance, 2 to 5 is 32.
Therefore, log of 32, it is 2, is 5.
is 5. So 3, the 4th is 81, right? So 3 times 3 is 9. So 9 times 9 is 81. So
So log of 81 base 3 is 4.
So what is the power of 3?
If I raise 3 to that power, this would be 81, that's 4.
So what's the power of 2 that 2 to that power
32 that's five. And this you can do basically for any number a now we
consider only integers like 2,3,4. In general it's possible to do for arbitrary
numbers. Yeah so that's the definition.
And usually we work with base two. In computer science, the base two usually
appears. So sometimes also other bases, but usually it's base two. And we write
LNG for log in base two. Now properties of logarithms. So these properties are
it's important and good sometimes useful in computations. So log of a in base a
is always 1 right? Because a to the power 1 is 8. So log of a base a is 1.
And log of one in any base a is zero because so you know by that a,
so any number raised to the power of zero is one.
So that's convention that a to the power of zero is one.
And so therefore log of one in any base a is zero.
So we're learning this logarithm function because it happens in the run times that we're going to see.
and it's a things about logarithm are important for computer science and it just always happens.
So we have to learn it.
Now another property is that log of x to the power p is equal to p times log of x.
So in other words, you can bring the p out of the logarithm, so you can bring the power
out of the logarithm and it becomes multiplicative.
So it's like this.
Now, all of these properties we're going to see they follow from just the definition.
Now I show some of them.
So, for instance, this one is very simple.
So, if you want to derive it from the definition and just,
For instance let's write Z.
so let me write log of x base a so I denoted by z then by definition I have a
power z is x. Now I can raise the both sides of this equation to power P. All
right so when you have two equal numbers the powers are equal. So therefore I get
to the Z to the power of P is equal to X to the P. But you know that so when you
have A to the Z to the power of P, so this is actually equal to A to the power
z times P, right? And then again, applying this definition, this we get that log of
X to the P base A is P times Z. Now Z was this log, so it's P times log of X
This is the proof, if you want, of this equation.
So I won't ask about these proofs, but I just want to show you
that these are really not difficult to derive from.
These are just follow from the definition.
So they're not strange things.
So, can anyone say what this symbol means here?
So, this.
So, what is this one?
So for instance, if you have something like say, a and then b.
So the equation, and then you have this and then b.
So this is implies.
Right so this is written as read as implies so a implies B
so these things you
Supposedly you should let in the discrete mass core so if a is true then B is true
That's this what it means now. This is a post ways implication so
This means that these two are equivalent
equivalent so whenever a through is true whenever these two a so now if you have
this is the first line here because this is the definition right so we have
equivalence and the second one is so again there's equivalence because you
can erase the two sides to the power or you can just remove the power they have
to be quoted from each other. So this is also two ways and here again is the
definition. So you go two ways. So sometimes, most often we use this one
which is an implication. So we from something we derive something else. But
if you also can go backwards then you have this.
Alright, so now this is an important property.
So power comes out of the logarithm.
So examples, so for instance 64 is 2 to the 6.
So we already know by definition that this is the log in base 2.
So it's already 6.
The answer is 6.
you can also see that by bringing this six outside.
So this becomes a six times log of two,
and log of two is one, so we get six.
Now there is a more general formula, which is this.
So if you have multiplication, x times y,
and you take the log, log turns this multiplication
addition. So log of X times Y is equal to log of X plus log of Y in any base. So I
don't say the base because it's just fixed so any base that you have. So log
of X times Y is log of X plus log of Y. Now this is very useful and is sometimes
used in for simplifying equations. So you might have a very large product you
have a product of many terms and you don't know what to do with it so but the
log I can turn the product into a addition and then you might be able to
do something you can you might be able to simplify or upper bound those I did
terms that you have and then you can again go back here remove the log so
going back and also to return the log so the inverse of the log is the
exponentiation function so raising to the exponent. So we discussed that also so
by raising the exponent then you can go back so therefore log can turn a
multiplication into addition. Now let's also show this, this is also very simple.
So let's have z1, for instance. This is log of x in base A. Let's try to see 2
For log of y in base a, then we have by definition that is a to base c1 is x and
to the zero is y. Now x times y is a times Z1 times a times Z2. And you know that
when you have multiplication of the powers and you have the same base there
there and the powers are added. So this is a to the z1 plus z2. Now from here
again if you apply the definition we have, so we get that log of x times y in base
A is Z1 versus Z2. So you can easily. So as you see basically because log is looks
the exponents so when you multiply two things the exponents add up all right
now this equation allows us to compute a little more logarithms so for instance
log of 24 you can write it as log of 23 times 3 so that's 8 times 3 and then 2
to the three is three times log of two plus log of three. Using this formula and
this term becomes three and this term is log of three. So now we cannot compute
log of three exactly. This is an irrational number so we can
approximate it but we as list we have computed log of twenty four in terms of
log of three. So it's something.
so using this formula and there's also a formula for the division so the x divided
by y so log of x divided by y is equal log of x minus log of y so this is also
can be taken to be a special case of this formula with negative powers.
yeah but it's also good to know that this also division is turned into
subtraction by the log. Again an example so for instance 1 over 1024 so log of
this is log of the top or 0 minus log of the bottom so 1024 is 2 to the 10 so
this becomes a negative 10. So log can become negative as you see here and for
numbers which are less than 1, log is negative. For 1, it's 0. For numbers which
are less than 1, it's negative. So any questions?
No question?
Okay. So, let's draw the graph of this function log of x.
So, let's say this is the x-axis, and this is log of x in base 2.
Now when x is 1, what is the log of x?
0.
So we get a point there.
So there's a point here.
So when x is 2, what is log of x?
So you have a point here.
And so when x is 4, what is log of x base 2?
2.
OK.
So we have here.
And then the next time you go up 1 is when you double this.
So 4, 5, 6.
This is 7, 8.
Log of 8 is 3, right?
2, 3.
any other point
it's so alright now you see if you want to go one more higher you have to double
the x so the next time you get four if you multiply it by 2 which is 16 so you
get one higher then again 64 and you see that as x becomes larger and larger
this function grows but it grows very slowly. So and as X becomes larger and
larger actually grows more slowly. And here actually it goes like this. The next
So here becomes negative.
Okay, now I talk more about this, but let's see some other important properties.
So, this is the formula that relates the different bases to each other.
So log of x in base b is equal to log of x in base a divided by log of b in base a.
Now, this side is a function of x.
Now, the top here is a function of x, but the bottom here is a constant number, right?
So log of b in base a is just one number.
It's not a function of x.
It's constant.
And because of that, so we see that for two numbers a and b, log of x in base b
and log of x in base a are within a multiplicative constant factor from each
other. So which means that one of them is just a constant times the other. So for
instance if we want to write log of x in base 3
that's log of X base 2 divided by log of 2 in base 3 right? So this is this formula.
Um, the other way around so this is log of 3 in base. So, b yes. So therefore if I
want to obtain the graph of log of X in base 3, I have to multiply this graph by
actually 1 over this, by the constant which is so 1 over log of 3 over 2. If you
multiply the graph by a constant just it doesn't change the shape of it much
right so it moves it a little bit but it doesn't change that for instance how it
grows it grows as before because it's a constant value now we see later that in
terms of the runtimes, we are interested in the growth of the function, so we are
not interested in the constant factors and because of that different bases for
us that they don't matter. So if we have, so we, if you have, we can compute the
runtime of a algorithm as log of, log of N in base 2, or log of N in base 3, it
doesn't matter for us, we say that it's a logarithm.
The base is not important because different bases are just a constant different from each other.
So, and constant factor is, we don't care about the constant factors.
Now, this is good, but it's much more important properties of logarithm.
So, first of all, it's increasing and it's unbounded.
So, increasing means that it's always increasing, right?
So it doesn't have any flat area.
So if increasing means that if X1 is less than X2,
then log of X1 with any base is less than log of X2.
This always increases.
So it's never equal to anything before.
So there is no flat areas.
here is always going higher and it's also unbounded so what does unbounded
mean can anyone say what's unbound doesn't have a bound so what does that
mean like there's no end yeah but that's again yeah it goes to infinity
infinity, basically. Right, so as X goes to infinity, the discussion log of X goes to
infinity. But now you, you might have seen some other functions which look like
this, but they don't go to infinity. Right, so they might actually, there are other
functions that they might become tangent to some line here, and they have limits.
but log of X doesn't have it actually it crosses every line that you draw
horizontal and goes higher would absolute value have a limit
absolutely no but you can easily build function something like one where X
squared or something like that. So, now it goes to infinity so it, it becomes
arbitrarily large. Now, the very important property of log is that it
grows very slowly. And what does it mean that it grows very slowly? So, basically
Basically, as X becomes larger and larger, lock of X, it also becomes larger, but it
doesn't become much larger.
It grows a little bit.
So in terms of runtime, would X be the input size?
We have N at the end.
And then the runtime would increase very slowly in terms of the input size.
So to see why it's good, I mean how it's very slow-growing.
So let's say we multiply x, so we send x to 2x, right?
So then if you have log of x, it goes to log of 2x.
But this is what?
log of 2x is log of x plus 1, right? So if you want to increase the value of log
just by 1, you have to double your equation. For instance, if you have
another function let's say x squared then if you replace x by 2x you get 4
times x squared. So actually it becomes much larger and you see that the
effect of it is much bigger as x becomes larger and larger and larger. So as
concrete examples let's say take for x to be let's say ten to the sixth right so
So if you send 10 to the sex into two times,
10 to the sex, the log of X is six times log of 10 goes into six times log of 10 plus one.
But if you have x squared, it's 10 to the power 12.
It goes to 4 times 10 to the power 12.
Right? Right.
So this I have to see my .
So if you have an algorithm whose runtime
is x squared, then an input of size a million.
So it takes some time, which is .
Right, so let me, okay.
So maybe I make this example a little better.
So let's not do this, because we don't have .
So let me write it.
Maybe. So let's have three functions.
So log of x.
So let's have two functions.
Log of x and x squared.
And imagine this is the runtime of a function of an algorithm.
then, and the input size let's say is 10 to the 6 is 1 million.
So for instance, we have 1 million numbers you want to sort
or some problem which you have size.
1 million is not very big.
So for instance, people that live in Chicago
are 1 more than 1 million.
So any algorithm you write, it has to work
on like billions of things.
So one million is not big.
But if an algorithm is quadratic, then it takes how much time?
So 10 to the 6th squared which is 10 to the 12th.
So it does that much operation.
But log of x is how much?
So log of 10 to the 6 is 6 times log of 10.
Log of 10 in base 2 is, so 2 to the 3 is 8.
So this is like 3.5 or something like that.
So 6 times 3 is 18.
So this is roughly speaking 20.
So around 20. So if you have an algorithm which is logarithmic in run time, on a million
input it just does 20 operations. So a quadratic algorithm does 10 times 12, even if it's a
linear algorithm which is just has the
running time as x itself, it still takes
10 to the 6th. So a logarithmic runtime
is very good. It's almost like an ideal
situation. So if you have an algorithm
which is logarithmic runtime, basically
you can do any number of input that you
want in very short time, seconds. Doesn't
matter how large the increase. And there's not many algorithms which are log of X.
So what you have seen for instance in the data structure course that you can
maintain a dictionary with log of X search time. So that means that basically
that's why you can do things in a computer so fast because for instance in
windows most of the things you do at the end is some search in a dictionary and
it does log of x operations. For instance when you do a click so log of x is so
you do some dictionary search but it takes log of x time but it's so small
that you don't notice it becomes real time but if it was a linear so if you
needed to do a linear search in a dictionary in linear time it wouldn't be
useful so you would see lags but log is almost nothing so it's no one notices
some something which is log so because of that dictionary operations are so fast
and they're actually not bound by this so it's more like memory access and
those things cost more than this factor log of x. Now for other algorithms so
for instance sort and this is not possible to do log of x let's say for
sort and these are there are reasons for that but for instance sorting we will
see later that we can do in N times log N times. Now because log of N is a very
slow growing function and it's almost a constant for all the practical purposes
so if I mean if you have for instance all the atoms in the world and take the
log of that it becomes something like a 1000 less than that so it's still some
constant. So this is against something like a linear. So if you have an
algorithm which is n times log of n, a run time is very good. It's something like
a linear runtime, in practice it's linear. Okay, so therefore the important
property of log is that it's a very slow-growing function and it's very good to have
algorithms with runtime log of x. Now, another property which I pointed to
earlier, so it's that the inverse of log is the exponentiation function, so log of
x in base A and A to the x are inverses of each other. Now, this is the graph of
log of X and so this means what? So any point here is the coordinator of it is X
log of X. Now the inverse function if there is, if you have a, for instance a
monotone function like this you can inverse it. So the inverse function would
if you give it a log of X it gives you X. Can anyone say how we can obtain the
graph of the inverse function from this graph?
Yeah.
Switching x and y.
And what does that correspond to in the graph?
Yes.
Yeah, switching x and y.
It corresponds to doing the reflection along the x equal y diagonal here.
you can take this diagonal and now you flip the graph along this diagonal so you get something
like this.
So this one goes again here.
So precisely what you do is that you become orthogonal to this and then you continue this
same amount.
And why is that?
flipping X and so if you do this then you have flipped X and Y and then this
graph now whatever you had X like X now this is like XX now this is the graph of
to the x, this is A to the x. So the inverse of logarithm is the A to the x
exponentiation function and you know that this exponential function grows
very fast. And so the same way that this grows very fast the log grows very
slowly. Now let's see this. Let me show you what this means that these are
inversed of each other. So if you have two functions f, so you have f of x and g of x,
then the inversing, they being inversed of each other means that, so when you compose them with each other,
you get the x back. So f of g of x, you want to be x, and g of f of x plus x. So if
you have these two, then f and g are inverse functions. Now, not all the
functions have inverses, right? So but if your function is monotone, like this
there is an inverse, so sometimes inverse is not a function. But now how to show
this? So the claim is that log and a to the x are inverses. So let's say F is log
of x in base a and g is a to the x so if I form f of g of x so it means that I
have to place g of x in place of x in f. So f of g of x becomes log of a in base a of a
to the X. But this I mean by definition of log this is the power of a which if I
raise a to that power I get a to the X, so that is X, right?
g of X is I have to put f of x in place of x in G so that's a to the power log
of X in base a so now log of X in base a by definition is the power of a that if
If you raise a to that power you get x so now we're raising a to that power so we get x.
So the combination of these two becomes the identity function or x.
So it shows that these are inverses of each other.
then so indeed so if you flip this you get the a to the x questions
All right, so these are very important facts about the log.
And so we need to learn two more things for the math background.
And that's one of them is arithmetic sequence
and after this the geometric sequence.
So in order to compute the runtimes, so sometimes, I mean,
most often you have a four loop.
And when you have a for loop, to compute the runtime you have to add the different iterations
of the for loop, and it's like adding the terms in a sequence.
And those sequences are usually arithmetic or geometric sequences.
And because of that we actually have to learn about the summations of these sequences.
Now, what's an arithmetic sequence?
It's very simple.
So it's you have a first term.
So the arithmetic sequence is built out of, you have a first term, and then you have a
difference d, and each time you add that difference to the previous term, you obtain the next
term.
So the next term is a0 plus d, and then you have a0 plus 2d, and so on.
So each two terms in arithmetic sequence, they differ by constant D, each two consecutive
terms.
And that's called an arithmetic sequence.
So there are many examples.
So for instance, the national numbers, like 1, 2, 3, so these are, they differ all, each
the consequent one difference by one or other numbers, even numbers. Alright, so
now if we have an arithmetic sequence, so we can add n terms of the sequence
together, so a1 through an, these are n terms of an arithmetic sequence. So if you
add them together there is a formula for the addition which is this so a one
plus a n times n over two. So to obtain the result of this addition so it's
enough to add the first term and the last term times n over two and is the
number of these these term set now this is actually not hard to see so can anyone
I suggest a way to prove this.
So, this actually moves a lot.
So let's say that S is this summation that we want to compute.
Now I can write this summation again starting from a n and going to a 1.
Okay, and then I add these together.
So, on the left-hand side, I get 2s.
Now, on the right-hand side, so the first two I add together, I get a1 plus an.
Now, the next two terms which are on top of each other are what?
So this here is a2 and this here is aN minus 1.
Right?
Now, I claim that if you add a2 plus aN minus 1,
again you get a1 plus aN.
Now, why is that?
because intuitively a2 is a1 plus d and a n minus 1 is a n minus d. So when you
add together the d's cancel out and you get the same a1 plus a n. So I write it
here, so a2 is a1 plus d. a n is a n minus 1 plus d. So therefore a n minus 1
is an minus d. Right? So if you add a2 and an minus 1, so you have added
d and subtracted d so you get the same a1 plus an. And this is true for any of
the other two terms which are on top of each other, and at the end you also have
a1 plus an so so you get n times a1 plus a1 so therefore s which was the
summation is equal to a1 plus an times n number two so that's the proof of this
equation. I won't ask about these proofs but again I want to see that these are
really not strange things and very easy to show. Alright so examples. So for
instance if you add numbers from 1 to 100 so the result is this. So a1 is 1, a n
is 100 times n over 2. So you got 100 of these numbers so you get this. And you
also notice this is a special case of this formula so if you want to add the
numbers from 1 to n. So you have this formula n times n plus 1 divided by 2. So
that's a special case of this. So another example. So if you add the odd
numbers from 1, let's say to 201. Now again you want to compute this
summation so again you add the first term plus the last term times the number
divided by 2. Now in this kind of situations you have to be careful to
count all of these correctly, right? So these are the odd numbers between 1 to
201. Now there is a systematic way of actually computing the number and that
is using the formula. So we had that. So the nth term is what? So it's a zero plus
n minus 1 times d. So that's the end term of your sequence. Now here you have a
A zero is one and B is two because you're considering the odd number.
So you differ by two and then you want to know which n is the 201.
And you solve this for n and you find the number of terms that you have.
of numbers. And then you can use it here.
Alright, so this here, so 2 times n minus 1 is 200. n minus 1 would be 100, n would be 101.
So the 201 is the 101st term of this.
So you have 101 many numbers here.
So you put it here and you can compute the sum.
All right.
So any questions?
So we have one slides about the geometric sequence. Now the geometric sequence is
similar but now this time you multiply a constant each time to obtain the next
term. So here we have so again you have the first term let's say a zero then
there's a ratio r so the next term is r times a zero. The next term is r squared
times a zero and so on, you continue like that so each term is obtained by
multiplying the previous one by r. So the ratio of two consecutive numbers is
fixed, is r. This is called a geometric sequence and this is actually also very
useful and as you see it's actually more important than the arithmetic. Now the
summation of N terms in a geometric sequence again as a formula which you
see here. So A1 times 1 minus R to the N divided by 1 minus R. And this is if
your R is not 1. Because if R is 1 they below their, in the fraction here it's
It's not meaningful because it becomes a zero.
So now what is the summation if R is one?
We divide it by zero?
Yes.
This thing is not meaningful but what is the summation if R is one?
So this formula doesn't apply anymore if r is 1.
But what is the summation?
Yeah, it's n times a.
Yes, it's n times a because if r is 1, you have your same term
because you are multiplying by 1, so you have a, a, a, a, a,
so n times, so you have n times a.
Now there is a very important special case which is if the absolute value of
your r, your ratio is less than 1, then you add all of the numbers of your
sequence so you infinitely many numbers if you can add all of them together and
they become finite and it's the value of that is a1 over 1 minus r. And that's
basically you can get from this formula if the absolute value of r is less than
than 1, r to the n goes to 0. So as n goes to infinity, r to the n becomes 0 and
so this becomes a 1 over minus r. This is very important formula so
conceptually is also important. So you have infinitely many numbers but they
become smaller and smaller and they actually become smaller in a fast way.
So, and then if you add all of them together you still get the finite number.
So you add infinitely many non-zero numbers you get a finite number.
And examples.
So this is the example of the first is r, is not 1, is not less than 1.
So what is r here in this example?
is 2, right? So we start from 1 and the
next term is 2, the next term is 4 and so
on. So that in general you can form, this
is the summation of powers of 2. So 1 plus 2
plus the square plus 2 to the third. Now
that one goes all the way to the 2 to the
10. But in general, you can go up to the n. Okay, anyone say what is this
summation? So if you add the powers of 2 up to the nth power, what do we get? So
So you can use that formula, but this is actually more renowned.
You get the net.
You get almost the next power.
So two to the n plus one minus one.
And you can get it from this formula.
And this is the behavior of the exponent exponential function.
So the next term is almost a summation of all previous terms.
So any function which is like this,
it behaves like an exponential function.
This is sometimes called the flat packing.
So you can pack all the powers of n, all the powers of 2
up to the nth power into the next power.
And you will get one room left in the next power.
have only one rule left. And here is, this is one all the way to, this is 2 to the
10 and this is 2 to the 11th, so minus 1. 2 to the 11 is 2014. Now this is again a
famous summation, which is the geometric sequence with the absolute value of r
less than 1. Here r is half so you have 1 plus half plus 1 over 4. The next term
is 1 over eighth and so on. Now if you add all of these together you get 1 over 1
minus half. And if you simplify that you get 2. So the summation of all these
numbers is 2. Now we use that in usually in the runtime computations in this form.
So we have a number n, and so instead of starting from 1,
you can start from n.
Then you will subdivide it by 2.
The next time, you divide it by 4, the next time
by 8, and so on.
Now, if you have n plus n over 2 plus n over 4,
plus n over h. So typical term is n over 2 to the i. If you continue like this to
infinity, you get what? So you get 2 times n, right? Because this is- so you can
factor out these ends so this this thing is equal to n times 1 plus a plus 1 over
4 and and this is 2 as we saw so this summation is 2 so that's 10 times 2 so
2 to n now here we a stop we stopped this summation we don't go to infinity
But we stop around 1.
So when this number becomes 1, we stop.
And that's why we have less than equal to 2n.
But there are still some terms which, if you go to infinity,
it becomes exactly equal to n.
But if you stop earlier, for instance, when you stop,
when you are just below 1, then you get less than equal to 2n.
OK.
and this we actually use this relation in communications so that's actually all
we wanted to learn about the math background questions so if no questions
Let's do a practice problem again.
All right.
So this is just, I mean, stand-up practice problems about the logarithms and the properties we saw.
And then also some problems about the arithmetic and geometric sequences.
So most of them are just applying the equations but there's a couple of them which is a little bit more than that.
This is also online.
And it will.
Thank you.
you
That's it.
so
Thank you.
I'm going to open the door.
um
You
And we're going to get a little bit of salt and salt.
Thank you.
.
Let's do it.
Thank you.
So, I saw some of these questions.
So, the first one is just applying the definition, it's just nothing serious.
So, let's do, for instance, this one, log of 2a, of 8 times 32.
This we can write as log of 8.
Okay.
1 times 22.
3 times 5a.
Now, this one, number 3.
we have to kind of, again use the same relation but instead you want to turn now summation
into multiplication. So the log plus log is log of 100 times 0.01. Now this is one, right?
log of 1 V 0. Now this is true for any base. So exercise 3 asks to solve this
question. This equation is also simple. Let's do one of them. So for instance this
last one again we use just a definition, four with the sum power
4 to the power half is x. Now 4 to the power of half is just the square root of 4. So x
should be 2. Questions?
Now this problems are also mostly applying the formula.
So this is just computing the summation. This one says that determine the 15th term
of the arithmetic sequence, but you just determined the D by subtracting two of them.
So it's 5, right? So 22 minus 17 is 5.
And then you can obtain any number any time that you want.
Now question 3 is a little bit tricky.
So it says that the sum of the first n terms of an arithmetic sequence is given by S of n.
So we know that sum of the n terms is S of n.
So it's 3n plus 5 divided by 2.
Right here.
n times 3n plus 5.
And it says find the common difference d.
now we have another formula for the
summation right so we can also say that
this summation is N is equal to a1 plus
a n times n over 2 but here we don't
have a1 and an, but we know that we can write an in terms of a1. So we can say
that an is just a1 plus n minus 1b, and then times n over 2.
Now we have two different ways of two different expressions for Sn. So the
problem says that Sn is this, Sn over 2 times 3n plus 5 and you also have the
formula. But in our formula we also have a1. So we have a1 and d. So how can we
obtain a d here. How to solve for d. So at first it seems that we actually have
two variables that we don't know. It's a1 and d, right? Now let's simplify the
right hand side in terms of the coefficients of n and n squared so I
have some term which is coefficient of n plus something times n squared right.
So coefficient of n is here 2A1 from here, and we have a 2 so we get, what is it we can just put half here,
have 2A1 minus d, right? So I get a minus d here, 2A1 here, so that becomes a
coefficient of n. The coefficient of n is squared, again I have a half from here,
and then from here I have d. It's just a d here, right? So this d times n times and
over 2 is this too. Now the problem says that this is equal to, now this left-hand
side, this guy, given by the problem, we can also write it in terms of the
coefficients of n and n squared. So we get 3 over 2 n squared plus 4 over 2
n which is fine so I just rewrote this
what is d is 3 right so now the point is that this has to be true for every n so
So if this has to be true for every n, so these two functions on the left and right,
they have to be the same polynomial function of n.
So to be the same polynomial function of n, then the coefficient of n has to be equal
to the coefficient of n here and coefficient of n squared, which is d over 2, has to be
equal to the coefficient of n squared, which is d over 2.
this the fact that s of n is this it doesn't give you for one number it gives
you that this summation is this function. Now you can make it equal to the other
function which we get using the other formula we have and it implies that D
has to be three. So there might be also other ways of solving this. This is one way to...
Because the two sides have to be the same polynomial function of N.
Okay, so here we have some again applications of the formulas for
geometric sequence and here there are two problems. So I solve this one, the
first one. It says that the ball is dropped from a height of a 100. So meters, it
doesn't matter what meters or what. So the ball you drop it back in, uh, from a
height of 100. And then it bounces back to three quarters of its height after
each bounce. So the next time it goes high, it bounces. So the ball goes
up and down. So this distance, this height is three quarters of 100. And the next
time it just be a little smaller and so on. It just continues like this. And
continues. So here, calculate the total distance traveled by the ball
before it comes to rest.
Well, it never comes to rest, right?
Because it goes up to infinity.
So, but the question was to add all of these distances
traveled by the ball.
So now, this is a geometric sequence.
But it's easier to actually add this distance also
to it so that it becomes all twice of this distance going off.
So I write it here so the summation that we want, let's say it's S,
100 plus S now is equal to, so the first distance is 200,
so going to this thing I added plus 100 going down.
The next distance is 3 over 4 times 200, right?
Because it goes, each one of these things is a 2 quarter, 100.
So overall, you get 3 over 4, 200.
And then the next one is 3 over 4 squared, 200.
Because the next bounce is 3 quarters of the previous bounce.
So in each time you multiply 3 over 4 to the previous term.
And so now we have one to add all these together.
Now we can factor the 200 out and then we have,
now the rest becomes 1 plus 3 over 4 plus 3 over 4 squared,
and so on.
Now this thing here is a geometric sequence, it's a summation of a geometric sequence.
The r is 3 over 4 is less than 1, right? So therefore, just using the formula you get
this summation is 200 plus 1 over 1 minus 2 over 4 times. And this becomes 4.
So this is 1 over 1 over 4 is 4.
So 4 times 200 is 800.
So this was S plus 100, so S becomes 700.
So therefore, the distance is travelled by the pole is 700 meters.
meters.
So if you could start from the second one, but if you add this first one hundred it comes a little bit nicer.
Two questions?
If no questions, I stop.
Let's go.
So,
Is there any homework?
I will submit later in the week.
I have two questions.
My first question is, is there ever going to be any in-class activities where we're
going to have our computer with us?
No.
OK.
So my question is, are you Persian?
I am too.
Yeah.
Yeah, I saw your name.
Yeah, I was like, I think that sounds Persian, but I couldn't tell, I wanted to ask.
You take care.
Thank you so much.
So,
Thank you.
.
You
Thank you.